Hey guys, Kee here from Kegland. Today
we're talking about our new Mark 5
regulators. Some of you guys will be
familiar with our older model, which was
the Mark 4. We've got several new
upgrades in the Mark 5 which really make
the whole regulator easy to use, easy to
maintain and just more reliable in
general. So let me get stuck into the
features and show you how this regulator
is quite different to the ones in the
past. So as soon as you look at the
regulator, you'll see it now says
patented tool free. And we've made this
as tool free as possible because who
wants to have to go and get a shift up
when you can just do the regulator up by
hand. If you look at the older regulators
like the Mark Fours for instance, or most
regulators out there in the market, they
require you to do it up with a nut here.
And the reason why a nut is really
required is because we use fairly hard
nylon washers or we did in the past. So
these nylon washers that are fairly hard
compound, they could be quite hard
wearing and last a long time. However,
from our experience, the reason why these
wear out is generally because people over
tighten this. So as soon as you put a nut
on there and you get people to tighten
these up, the temptation is that people
get a spanner, get a lot of leverage and
they can do it up overly tight and then
they damage this nylon washer. So we
generally always ship these with a spare
which is zip tied onto the regulator like
that. So you've got to back up just in
case that one wears out. However, we
really thought that it was time for us to
address this because that was one of the
parts that it's a bit annoying if you
happen to be halfway through a party and
don't ever. Washer So what we do now is
now with the tool free design it's all a
hand wheel like this so really easy don't
need any tools and you can do it up like
that and you're probably saying well how
can I get the torque required to do this
up tight enough to seal and that's
because we've changed the spigot design
So if you look at the spigot design, this
now uses a much softer compound here. The
actual you can see the o-ring is embedded
into the brass spigot here So if you
needed to change this you could pick it
out and then put another one in but
honestly you should never be able to
damage this because as you can see. It's
got when you actually do these two parts
up together like that, the brass will
start to bottom out once you get to the
correct level of compression. So you
can't really over compress this one
easily at all due to how it's designed
being with that softer seal. All you need
is to basically do this up by hand like
that and then once you feel a bit of
resistance, give it another little half
turn and then it's done. So that's now
holding pressure can turn the cylinder.
As you can see, I've got full bottle
pressure on that. It's not leaking at
all. So fantastic. Really, really easy
look, if you're really weak or for some
reason you don't have very good grip,
look, you could still get, you know, a
spanner onto this connection here and
tweak it up with the spanner if you
really needed to. But really a lot of
that temptation for damaging the seal is
has been removed because of this hand
wheel on there. So with the mark fives
and the mark fours, we have always put
the class 2.5 gauge on there. I should
make mention to that because a lot of
people want to get, you know, pretty good
accuracy on the gauges and the most
common other homebrew gauges that you
would get out there would be a class 3.
Look, it's not a massive difference, but
when you say class two or three or four
or five, basically that number relates to
its percentage accuracy over the gauge
range. So if you've got a gauge that goes
up to let's say 100 PSI, then if it's a
class 3, then you get plus or. -3 PSI for
the gauge range. So if it's a class 2.5,
it's slightly more accurate. You're
getting ±2 1/2% of the gauge range, so 2
1/2 PSI in that instance. If it has less
pressure on the gauge, obviously you get
higher accuracy at the lower pressures,
but you can't go as high on the
regulator. One other thing to note, which
some people get a bit confused and should
be aware of is you should. The needle
should never exceed more than 80% of the
gauge range either. So if you're ever
getting really high, you should be
upgrading to a higher pressure gauge. We
do. See people over crank these up even
I've seen a lot of home Brewers go past
the end of the gauge and then that really
damages the cogs inside the gauge as
well. So just be aware of that. So the
other thing we've upgraded and I felt
this was really important with the mark 5
is the output here. So look, we undered
about this because some people find this
a bit confusing when you're a new
homebrewer. And previously we didn't used
to put any ball valve to isolate the
gaslight on the output. We just used to
have this duo type fitting and this would
essentially. Go on like that and push the
gas line in. So that was it. But we did
get a number of customers say they kind
of like some of the other brands of
regulated because they gave them a ball
valve on the output like this. So I know
tap right do this for instance. The other
thing was with integrated check valve
into this ball valve mechanism. So one of
the most common areas where a homebrew
gauge will get damaged is because liquid
ingress coming in through here. If liquid
gets in here, it starts to cause
corrosion. That corrosion then starts to
cause problem with the regulator
internally. Now certainly you can take it
apart and clean it out, but it's a
massive pain and sadly a lot of those
regulators get liquid inside end up going
to the bin because people can't bother
don't don't have the know how to fix it
or the tools to fix it at home. So. You
know, we thought it was important for us
to put a check valve in there. It's just
one thing to remember that obviously, you
know when you're using this regulator,
you have to obviously remember to open
the ball valve. So when it's in this nine
degree, that means off. So no gas is
going to flow out when you go like that,
it's turned on as well. So you can
basically turn that on. The other thing
we've done is upgraded the duo type
fitting. So this is now a metallic duo
type fitting and it comes with an 8mm as
standard on the regulator. Makes it
really, really easy to fit the gas line.
So literally all I do is just push that
in there and then I'm done. It's giving
me a good airtight seal being a duo tight
fitting. It's also good double O-ring in
there as well. So if you take this out,
you can see in there we actually use the
new Gen. 2 duo type fitting. So these are
the Gen. 2 Geo type fittings where we've
put. Two O rings with a silicon and EPDM.
So you get the best of both worlds with
with regards to its ceiling performance.
But really the check valve does make a
massive difference. It's just something
you have to remember that, you know, if
you crank the gas up like this and if you
pull the pressure release valve here,
that is only releasing the gas pressure
from the check valve upstream. Obviously
it can't with the check valve in there.
You're not releasing gas downstream in
the keg itself. But for that same reason,
you don't have that risk of sucking
liquid back up in there. Just remember
that when you're using it, or if you're a
newbie, if you need to release pressure
from the keg, go and pull the pressure
release valve on the top of the keg
itself. So let's say I've got, for
instance, this. Oxy bar 8
liter keg. I'm going to pull it here.
Pull this pressure release valve here.
Not that one on the regulator. Now,
the other reason why it's a tool free
design is really because of the
maintenance. So if you were to get one of
these older regulators or really any
regulator in industry, home Brewers are
particularly tough on regulators for a
few reasons. Firstly, home Brewers are
generally using small cylinders like
this. Now if you've ever opened one of
these cylinders, it's very common for
them to have a little bit of corrosion
from the metal inside the cylinder. Now
if you've got a really big cylinder like
this, it probably never gets inverted,
tipped upside down or something like
that. So therefore all that rust or you
know. Or aluminum oxide, If it's an
aluminum cylinder, we'll sit at the
bottom of the cylinder. It always
happens. These cylinders basically don't
have a valve taken out for 10 years at a
time. So any contamination just sits
there. But if you're a home Brewer,
because you've got a small cylinder, you
probably sometimes put it sideways.
Sometimes it goes upside down inside the
back of a car seat or something like
that. You're driving around and because
of the we're using these small cylinders,
the chance of contamination coming out
through the cylinder into the regulator
is way, way higher. The other thing with
home Brewers is we're connecting these
two things. Like, you know, overly full
beer kegs and stuff like that. Some
people don't have check valves in place
and people are pulling pressure release
valves like this and often sucking liquid
back up into the regulator. You know,
often a big problem as well. The other
thing is some people have these
regulators in fridges in high moisture
environment. Moisture gets in there so
you get brass corrosion can cause
contamination as well. The other last
thing as well is when you turn regulators
up to full. Pressure like this and
you do force carbonation and you
increasing and decreasing the pressure.
Or if you're pulling the pressure release
valve and you see that needle jumping up
and down, that aggressive use of the
regulator where you've got the seat and
seat cap internally bouncing up and down.
Has a much much higher chance of those
two brass components wearing off and the
bits of bits, small flakes of brass
coming through the regulator and getting
stuck under the seat and seat cap. So
honestly, home Brewers are far tougher on
regulators than even a lot of commercial.
Applications where regulators are used
and sadly enough, a lot of those types
of instances with contamination, the
smallest flake of dirt rusts, you know,
aluminium oxide or even, you know, liquid
getting in there. If it gets under the
seat and seat cap, it can cause what we
call pressure creep. Now I don't know if
you guys seen this before, but pressure
creep is when you essentially set a
pressure on the gauge and then gradually
the pressure keeps building and building
and building and then it blows the
pressure release valve. So no matter what
brand of regulator you got, if moisture
gets in there even, it's like you know,
you can get the world's most expensive
brand, you're going to get this problem
if liquid gets in there and it's a real
nightmare. So typically what you would be
required to do is you're required to
either mount. To something somehow get
into advice look, we've got this special
cradle that we use to hold on to this
regulator allowing us to take off the
whole bonnet. Now I've already loosened
this one so I can just undo it by hand
like that. Now when you take this apart,
it's not a job which everybody can do to
be honest with you it's a bit of a pain
in the bum and some people don't have the
tools or no advice at home and if you're
in the field or in a party or an event,
you certainly don't have this type of
equipment to do this type of job but it
would require you to take this apart take
the. Wanted assembly off like that you
would then and this is actually one that
has been returned to us. A regulator's
not working funnily enough. Open it up
and there's corrosion everywhere because
there's been liquid get inside this
regulator and this is unfortunately quite
common. We'd see this from time to time
because many, many people don't use check
valves anyway, I'll take this out. You
can see that this whole seat and seat cap
assembly has quite a lot of you know,
corrosion on it like that. So I'm not
sure if you can see in the camera there I
might do a zoom in later, but essentially
that corrosion. Has caused this to
essentially become a pressure creep
scenario now this one for the customer
they were going to throw it out but with
the new mark fives there's so much easier
to maintain and for this type of issue
which you know it's still possible to
happen it now can be done in the field
with no tools whatsoever So what we've
done is we've actually got.
This knob here, and if I unscrew the knob
from the front of the regulator, you turn
it upside down and you can see I've got a
handy little M8 on 8 or metric. 8mm hex
here and that basically Allen key there
is so you can undo the back of the
regulator. So at the back here, instead
of us having to remove this whole bonnet,
which is real pain and a lot of people
didn't have the tools or a cradle or vice
to do that, you basically just take this
off. You don't even have to disconnect
this from the cylinder. Obviously if you
have it connected cylinder, you've got to
make sure the CO2 is turned off, but you
can basically still have this on the
cylinder and within a few seconds I can
just under the back of the regulator like
this with that 8mm hex or Allen. That
you've got under here. Use this knob from
the front of the regulator and undo this
**** so you can see that 8mm hole there.
You basically just go like that and you
take the back of the regulator out. So
really easy, no tools required. I could
do this in the field with really nothing
at all. A spring is going to fall out
like that. Look, if you've got small
fingers, you can probably just pick this
out. It is a little bit easier if you
have something sharp like a toothpick or
something like that. Then I've got the
this little seal for that **** which goes
on there. And then last but not least,
I've got this part here, which is this.
Is what we call the seat cap assembly. So
this here you can see is made out of
ultra high molecular weight polyethylene
and this is the only regulator which I've
ever seen where we've designed it the
entire seat cap out of ultra high
molecule 8 PE. The reason why we've done
this is because if you get other
regulators, this is usually a brass part.
Now obviously if you've got a brass part
which is bouncing up and down inside this
hole so you know when you're using a
regulator as I was saying homebrewers
sometimes. This is pressure release
valve, the needles jumping up and down
and stuff like that. Those types of
instances will mean the seat and seat cap
assembly, like this piece here is
basically bouncing up and down inside
this hole. And if you've got brass
rubbing up against brass, especially if
there's any corrosion or contamination
around, the chance of a tiny flake of
brass ending up on this seat cap is way,
way higher. So, you know, the failure
rate when you got brass on brass rubbing
components is much, much higher. You're
much more likely to pressure creep
situation and that's sort of unavoidable.
Because that's how all other regulators
are made at the moment. But one thing you
can do is to greatly reduce the issues is
simply go a plastic on brass type of
fitting. So because it's entirely molded
out of plastic, when this is rubbing up
and down on the inside bore of the
regulator, the chance of rubbing off a
flake of brass is way, way less. But even
in the instance that some bit of brass
does get caught on the, you know, top of
the seat gap here, it's not going to
prevent this from sealing up against the
face at the bottom of this hole. Which
means that you know, it's super easy to
clean out. So I can basically just take
this off and I can clean this off with a
bit of a cloth or something like that and
then just jam it back in there. So
literally within a few seconds, I've put
my regulator back together, fixed the
pressure creep situation without even
having to reach for a spanner or anything
like that from the workshop. So super
easy out in the field. You could do this
with really anything at all and then away
you go. So screw that on and then go back
to the front of the regulator put. Knob
back in and, you know, back up and
running with really hard beady fuss.
Honestly, that's a 32nd job. Now, a
highly recommended accessory for you
guys, if you're going to get a good
regulator, is get yourself a gauge guard.
They're really not expensive and it is
such a pain when you damage a gauge. We
see so many homebrewers who buy these
gauges like this. They put them on a
cylinder, think, Oh yeah, it's all hunky
Dory, I'm all good. They've got a kid
that comes along or they trip over a gas
line or something. Like that sends this
cylinder sideways and boom, if this
cylinder falls over sideways, all it has
to do is happen once, it's going to
damage the gauge. A lot of customers at
home don't have the tools to really
easily change and gauge themselves. So
look for the sake of like such a cheap
accessory, get yourself one of these
gauge guards because they're so cheap to
fit. We've got stainless steel ones, I
think on the website. We're also thinking
about doing these black powder coated
steel ones as well, but they fit onto the
gauges like this. Like that. And the
other thing is even with the gauge guard
fitted, these new models of gauge guards
that were starting to make now still have
that hole at the back of the gauge guard.
So you can still, you know, even get
access like take that knob off and get
access to the back to service and
maintain the seat and seat cap assembly
if you needed to. But that just sits on
the front. And then you've got these
three little screws in here which you can
fit to the back of the regulator that
attaches the gauge guard on here like so.
So you have to do these three. Like that
and then.
Boom and boom boom. And literally this
gauge guard here, it can handle a fairly
large wax. So if you're got even a larger
6K gas cylinder, we tested these gauge
guards on the cylinders falling over onto
concrete and the gauges were perfectly
fine. So look, small investment. Save
yourself the heck in the long run. People
who think ahead, get the gauge guard. Now
before I disappear, I'm also going to say
we go to a high level of QC when
it comes to these regions. There's every
single regulator that you find in a box
like this will basically have two tests
done on it at least. So first let me go
to 1 1/2 times the working pressure, both
on the inlet side and the outlet side to
make sure that the gauge holds its
maximum pressure. The other thing we do
is a pressure decay test. So we've got a
large manifold which is set up with 3000
PSI. What we do is pressureize all the
gauges and pressurize the output, turn
the gas off and make sure the pressure
doesn't drop. So we basically measure
that pressure decay if it gets picked up.
Will take apart the regulator and fix
that problem. So when you get a box like
this, you know that the regulator has
been tested, you open it up and it's
going to work straight away. The other
thing is, you know, because we do such
high level of testing and we're sure that
the gauges are great, we give a five year
warranty on these regulators. So now with
any of the Kegland branded ones, you know
you've got a regulator, it's going to
last you many, many years to come and
going to give you lots of reliable
service. That is pretty much it. If you
guys got any other requests for new stuff
you want to make or changes to
regulators, definitely put it in the
comments below. We always love to hear
from our customers. A lot of the ideas
and changes we make are really from
feedback from our valuable customers like
yourself. The other thing we'd love you
to do is sign up to our Facebook homebrew
community group. So go to that on
Facebook search Kegland homebrew
community group. You'll find it straight
away and join that one. And of course,
sign up to the to the YouTube channel
bottom right hand corner. Hit subscribe
now. Of course, hit the notification
bell, Bing, Bing and that way you will
get notified as soon as we launch new
products or do videos like this. That's
it and I'll see you guys next time. Bye.